בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ט״ז, Tes Zayin, 16,
and we pick up at the top of ט״ז עמוד א׳. Tes
Zayin amud aleph. That would make it the 29th day of the
עומר, Omer, right? The add-13 rule. Okay, so and we are in
the middle of the second פרק, perek, or we just began the
second פרק, perek, which moves us beyond שלא לשמו Shelo Lishmo and
gets us into the general question about all the different circumstances which
invalidate a sacrifice, going from thought to more concrete things, or to
more things that relate to the status of the person. And we
had a whole list of types of people who, if they did
the עבודה, avoda, invalidate the sacrifice, although we started with the קבלת
הדם, Kabbalat HaDam, not the שחיטה, shechita, because the שחיטה shechita is
כשר kosher with a non-כהן, kohen, so we wanted to have the
full list, so we started with the קבלת הדם. Kabbalat HaDam. And
we have started with the idea that a non-כהן kohen invalidates, and
the גמרא Gemara wants to know not just now the point here
is not just that the person violates and is not permitted to
bring the sacrifices under these various case states, you're not a כהן,
kohen, you're drunk, you're a whatever, you're טמא, tamei, etc., etc., but
that it actually invalidates. So how do we know that's true by
the non-כהן? kohen? So the גמרא Gemara learned it out based on
from a קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, a צד השווה, Tzad HaShaveh, from
the case of somebody who some of a כהן kohen who has
a blemish, and a כהן kohen who is טמא, tamei, and they
invalidate, and therefore the same is true about a non-כהן. kohen. Okay,
and the general rule is anybody who's not allowed to bring invalidates.
So the גמרא Gemara is now going to ask, okay, we get
that that's the rule, but how do we know that a non-כהן
kohen is not allowed to bring? So we pick up with that
on ט״ז עמוד
א׳, Tes Zayin amud aleph, go one, two, three, about five lines
from the top.
הצד השוה שבהן, Hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator between טמא tamei
and בעל מום, Baal Mum, שמוזהרין, shemuharin, that they are prohibited against
bringing when they are a כהן, kohen, when they are in that
state. ואם עבדו חיללו, Ve'im avdu chilalu, and if they did the
עבודה, avoda, they desecrated it, they invalidated it. אף אני אביא זר,
Af ani avi zar, I will bring a non-כהן, kohen, שמוזהר, shemuhar,
he is foresworn against, he is prohibited to do the עבודה, avoda,
ואם עבד חילל, ve'im avad chillel, and if he does it, he
invalidates it. So the גמרא Gemara says: מנלן דמוזהר? Menalan demuzhar? Now,
where do you know that a non-כהן kohen is not allowed to
do the עבודה? avoda? אי מוינזרו, Ei mivinnazru, if it's from the
verse
"וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל", Veyinnazru mikodeshei benei Yisrael, where the simple sense
of that verse is talking about a כהן kohen who is טמא,
tamei, but we had a possible reading of it to include a
non-כהן. kohen. So if that's true, חילול בגופיה כתיב ביה. Chillul begufei
ketiv bei. If you're going to read that to be about a
non-כהן, kohen, which is not how we're reading it now, but if
you're going to read that to be referring to a זר, zar,
then you don't need to make a צד השווה, Tzad HaShaveh, common
denominator. That verse itself explicitly says "וינזרו מקדשי בני ישראל ולא יחללו".
Veyinnazru mikodeshei benei Yisrael velo yechalelu. So the simple sense of that
verse is about טמא, tamei, but if it's about a non-כהן, kohen,
you don't need to go any further. So clearly that's not how
we're reading that verse. So we're saying a צד השווה, Tzad HaShaveh,
so where are we going to get the sense that a non-כהן
kohen is prohibited? אלא מוזר לא יקרב אליכם, Ela mivezar lo yikrav
aleichem, a זר, zar, a non-כהן, kohen, cannot come close to you,
meaning and do the service that you the כהנים kohanim do.
So that's pretty explicit. Okay, so since a non-כהן kohen is not
allowed to do the עבודה, avoda, the צד השווה Tzad HaShaveh tells
us that he also violates the קרבן korban and, you know, invalidates
the קרבן, korban, I should say. איכא למפרך, Ika lemifrach, but you
can challenge this צד השווה. Tzad HaShaveh. מה לצד השוה שבהן שכן
לא הותרו בבמה? Ma letzad hashaveh shebahen sheken lo hutru bebama?
The case of a זר zar is allowed to bring outside of
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right? The same way, I mean, it
really gets to the idea that a כהן kohen is like one
of the כלים keilim of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, you know,
it's one of the part of the apparatus of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. So therefore, only in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash does
it have to be with a כהן. kohen. Out of the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it doesn't have to be with a כהן. kohen.
But ironically, out of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the idea that
you cannot have a מום, mum, a blemish, still applies, which is
like really strange, as we assume מום mum goes with כהן. kohen.
Okay, so the problems of טומאה tuma and מום mum still apply
out of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but a non-כהן kohen does
not. So maybe
even though a blemish and being טמא tamei
invalidate, maybe they invalidate because those are universal, those are problems that
exist even out of the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, whereas a non-כהן
kohen that doesn't exist, maybe if he does it in the בית
המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he doesn't invalidate. Okay, that's not a bad סברא.
svara. I mean, if you have a guy that sometimes is okay,
even though the sometimes is in a completely different scenario out of
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, but maybe he's not so out of
bounds, maybe he doesn't invalidate.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: לא תימא טמא יוכיח. Lo tima
tamei yochiach. So fine, put טמא tamei aside. אלא אימא אונן יוכיח.
Ela eima onain yochiach. We'll do it from the common denominator between
a בעל מום Baal Mum and an אונן, onain, a כהן kohen
who has just suffered a loss, a person in the family just
died. Okay, מה לאונן? Ma le'onain? By itself, you can't apply that
to a זר, zar, because
מה לאונן... Ma le'onain... can eat
מעשר, maiser, בעל מום baal mum can even eat קרבנות. korbanot. So
it's not about the inability to eat
מעשר. maiser. And וחזר הדין לא ראי זה כראי זה, v'chazar hadin
lo rei zeh k'rei zeh,
so again, מעשר maiser and אונן onen and בעל מום baal mum
each have unique characteristics. Let's try to identify the
הצד השוה שבהן, hatzad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator is what? That
they are both prohibited and they invalidate. So a זר zar is
prohibited and he invalidates. And now you're going to come and say,
"Ah, but wait a minute, but they... but you know a זר
zar can bring outside the בית המקדש." Beit HaMikdash. So presumably the
answer will be for introducing אונן, onen, it sounds like the גמרא
Gemara wants to say maybe an אונן onen can also bring outside
of the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Let's take a look. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara is going to say הכא נמי ליפרך מה להצד
השוה שבהן שכן לא הותרו בבמה. hacha nami lifrach mah lahatzad hashaveh
shebahen sheken lo hutru b'bamah. One minute though, those guys can't bring
on a במה, bamah, and a זר zar can bring on a
במה. bamah. No, so the גמרא Gemara says מתקיף לה רב סמרא
בריה דרבא, maskif lah Rav Samra breih d'Rava, ומאן לימא לן דאונן
אסור בבמה? u'man leima lan d'onen assur b'bamah?
Whoever told you that an אונן onen couldn't bring on a במה?
bamah? You don't have any basis to say that. דאמר שרי בבמה?
de'amar shari b'bamah? I love that, it's like the גמרא Gemara says,
"Says who?", okay? Maybe an אונן onen could bring on a במה.
bamah. So that allows us to make a הצד השוה, tzad hashaveh,
since we have no evidence that an אונן onen can't bring on
a במה, bamah, we're going to assume an אונן onen can bring
on a במה bamah unless proven otherwise. And therefore the הצד השוה
tzad hashaveh shows us that even people that can bring on a
במה, bamah, if they're prohibited in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, are
invalidated. And the same is true about a non-כהן. kohen. Since he's
prohibited in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, he invalidates. So that's one
לימוד limud from the הצד השוה tzad hashaveh of אונן onen and
בעל מום. baal mum. Okay, רב משרשיא אמר אתיא קל וחומר מיושב.
Rav Mesharshiya amar atya kal v'chomer mi'yoshev.
It's a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from a כהן kohen who does
it while he is sitting, which is interesting because now we're sort
of moving from a personal status to a way in which the
עבודה avodah is done. Okay, so מה יושב שאוכל, mah yoshev she'ochel,
a person who is sitting can still eat the קרבנות, korbanot, eat
even the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, you don't have to eat your
חטאת chatat standing up. אם עבד חילל, im avad chillel, but if
he does the עבודה avodah sitting, he invalidates it. זר שאינו אוכל,
zar she'eino ochel, a זר zar who's not allowed to eat the
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, אינו דין שאם עבד חילל? eino din she'im
avad chillel? How much more so does he invalidate. Okay, so again,
like a type of a קל וחומר kal v'chomer from a כהן
kohen who's sitting. No, מה ליושב שכן פסול לעדות? mah l'yoshev sheken
pasul l'edut? Okay, so how... no, a יושב yoshev maybe has greater
invalidity than a non-כהן kohen because if somebody is sitting they can't
bear testimony. Now if you ask me like what the heck does
bearing testimony have to do, you know, if anything you might want
to say what about sitting you're not allowed to do שמונה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei while you're sitting? It's a little more relevant to the
world of קרבנות. korbanot. I don't know what sitting has to do
with bearing testimony, how is it at all relevant? But so the
גמרא Gemara says ah, maybe sitting is a special category. So you
can't assume just because you're invalid at sitting, by sitting, that because
sitting is invalid by a lot of things, you can't assume that
a non-כהן kohen is invalid. So we're going to again go to
a הצד השוה, tzad hashaveh, okay? ואפילו תימא יושב תלמיד חכם. v'afilu
teima yoshev talmid chacham. Ah, no, sometimes we let somebody, you know,
bear testimony when they're sitting. If it's a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
we show them respect and we let them give their testimony while
they're sitting, which would seem to indicate if we're going to make
an exception for a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, it would seem to
indicate that it's not a real invalidity to begin with, it's just
an issue about, you know, sort of like propriety or whatever. But
anyway, מה לשם יושב שכן פסול לעדות? mah l'shem yoshev sheken pasul
l'edut? No, as long as there's an example of a יושב yoshev
that's invalid by עדות, edut, even if there are some examples that
aren't, that makes יושב yoshev weightier and you can't learn out from
the case of sitting. And the גמרא Gemara says שם יושב לא
פריך. shem yoshev lo parach. He's saying, "Nah, don't tell me that
there's an example of sitting that's invalid. Since there's a type of
a sitting that is valid, we can still make the קל וחומר."
kal v'chomer. Okay, and therefore if sitting
invalidates sacrifice, and sitting is not weighty, so weighty, because there are
cases of sitting that you can even bear testimony, so don't try
to sort of bracket it because of that. So if sitting... and
therefore you can also say the same, if a case of sitting
invalidates, a non-כהן kohen also invalidates.
ואם תימצי לומר פריך, v'im timtzi lomar parach, and if you're going
to say, "No, at the end of the day you can't learn
out from sitting because there are cases of sitting which is invalid
by bearing testimony, even though there are some cases like a תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham where you can bear testimony, sitting is weightier, you
can't learn out from that," so אתיא מיושב ומחד מהנך. atya mi'yoshev
u'michad mehanach. Make a common denominator between יושב yoshev and one of
the other cases we had: a בעל מום, baal mum, טמא, tameh,
an אונן, onen, any one of those other people. Okay, and you
do the common denominator, and the common denominator tells you that even
if it's, what do you call it, that anybody who's prohibited invalidates.
Okay, so now of course, as we've known, the challenge of the
common denominator was, "Oh, but those guys are invalid by a במה,
bamah, a non-כהן kohen is כשר kasher by a במה." bamah. So
if we're going to throw in the idea of sitting, the goal
here, the only problem we really need to solve here about our
whole הצד השוה tzad hashaveh is we don't want all of the
cases to be cases that are פסול בבמה, pasul b'bamah, because a
זר... zar... and we want to make sure that the הצד השוה
tzad hashaveh eliminates that way of narrowly defining it. So therefore what
we're looking to do is to say that the case of... So
therefore what we're looking to do is to say that the case
of a כהן kohen who is sitting is actually going to be
כשר בבמה kasher b'bamah and then we'll say so you have these
people that are invalid that are not allowed to do it and
they invalidate and therefore a non-kohen also's not allowed and invalidates and
don't tell me oh but a non-kohen can work can do it
on the במה bamah among those people that invalidate is these people
that also are allowed to do it on a במה. bamah. So
who is that? So how do you know that a יושב yoshev
is permitted to do the עבודה, avodah, you can do it sitting
on a במה? bamah? So the גמרא Gemara says ואם תמצא לו
v'im timtzo lo so the גמרא Gemara says יושב דכשר בבמה מנלן?
yoshev d'kasher b'bamah minalan? אמר קרא amar kra לעמוד לפני ה' לשרתו.
la'amod lifnei Hashem l'sharto. How do you know you have to be
standing when you do the עבודה? avodah? It's because it says to
stand before God to serve Him. לפני ה' lifnei Hashem ולא לפני
במה. v'lo lifnei bamah. The whole difference of a במה bamah is
a במה bamah is you can you know pray anywhere to God,
but it doesn't mean that that's the place of God, right? The
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is the מקום makom of the שכינה. Shechinah.
That's where you know ועשו לי מקדש ושכנתי, v'asu li mikdash v'shachanti,
you know, I will dwell there. So the idea of לפני ה'
lifnei Hashem is not a concept about a במה. bamah. You could
be מקריב makriv but not a sense it's not everywhere you build
a במה bamah God is assumed to be like in a you
know more present than anywhere else. Okay so therefore we have a
צד השוה tzad hashaveh that these various people, בעל מום, ba'al mum,
טמא, tamei, אונן, onein, יושב, yoshev, all these people are prohibited and
they invalidate, so a זר zar also who's prohibited and invalidates, and
amongst that list of people are people who also even can do
it on a במה. bamah. So don't try to say a זר
zar shouldn't invalidate because he can do it on a במה, bamah,
some of those people also can do it on a במה bamah
and nevertheless they invalidate, so the same is true about a זר.
zar. So that gets us זר. zar. We're going to go through
the list. אונן. onein. Each one of these we're going to want
to know where they how do we know that they invalidate along
the way because this is the nature of the צד השוה tzad
hashaveh which is what the גמרא's Gemara most going to return to.
We're going to also mostly point out how we know they're not
allowed to. But the focus is how do we know that they
invalidate?
אונן מנלן? onein minalan? How do you know that an אונן onein
invalidates? דכתיב d'chsiv by the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol ומן המקדש לא
יצא ולא יחלל. u'min haMikdash lo yeitzei v'lo yechalel. For the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol cannot leave the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and even
though he does not leave the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash he will
not desecrate the sacrifices because he is allowed to or he's obligated
whatever to stay in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash even if he's
an אונן, onein, even if a family member just died. So for
him he does not desecrate the sacrifices, so the implication is האחר
שלא יצא חילל. ha'acher shelo yatza chilel. Somebody else who would stay
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a normal כהן kohen who is
not told to stay in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, a normal
כהן kohen who's supposed to become טמא tamei you know for an
immediate relative. If he chooses to stay in the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash even if he didn't become טמא tamei just because a relative
immediately relative died, he would actually desecrate. So that's a pretty good
read. He doesn't, the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol doesn't go out and
doesn't desecrate, a normal כהן kohen who were to stay would desecrate.
Okay, positive commandment to do with the לווית המת? levayas hameis? Is
that what it is?
Yeah, for the for a normal כהן? kohen? Right. Yeah so a
normal כהן kohen is obligated actually and the גמרא Gemara even says
מטמאים אותו בעל כרחו, metamim oso b'al korcho, you actually force him
to become טמא tamei to tend to his immediate relative. Right.
But if you didn't like the relative or...
exactly. Well we're talking about immediate, we're talking about father, mother, right
right. But that is correct yes. I know sometimes you don't like
your immediate relatives also. Okay anyway. But yes, the גמרא Gemara even
says that there was one כהן kohen who refused to become טמא
tamei and they forced him to become טמא. tamei. Okay that part
of the way of showing respect to this relative is that it
goes so far that you even you know violate and compromise your
sanctity of כהונה kehunah for the sake of tending to the dead.
Okay. So that's what you learn a lot of the basic הלכות
halachos about about אבילות aveilus and so on are learned from the
laws of כהנים. kohanim. Okay.
רבי אליעזר אומר מהכא. Rabbi Eliezer omer meihacha. We learn it from
the following פסוק. pasuk. הן הקריבו. hen hikrivu. Okay, so when משה
Moshe says to אהרן Aharon why did your why did you burn
the חטאת chatas you know when during the מילואים, miluim, right we
just read this relatively recently, why did you burn the חטאת chatas
you know you should have eaten it במקום קדוש bemakom kadosh even
though you know נדב ואביהוא Nadav v'Avihu died you were supposed to
eat it. And אהרן Aharon replies הן היום הקריבו את חטאתם ואת
עלתם לפני ה' ותקראנה אתי כאלה ואכלתי חטאת היום הייטב בעיני ה'.
hen hayom hikrivu es chatasam v'es olasam lifnei Hashem vatikrena osi ka'eleh
v'achalti chatas hayom hayitav b'einei Hashem. They ate, they I mean it's
a very hard פסוק pasuk to parse. הן היום hen hayom did
they today or they today offered their חטאת chatas and עולה olah
and these things happened to me, if I would have eaten it
would it have been good in the eyes of God? So like
huh? What are you saying? So the basic way the חז"ל Chazal
are parsing this פסוק pasuk there's two ways okay. But the basic
point is that נדב ואביהוא Nadav v'Avihu died, so they were אוננים.
onenim. Okay. Now אלעזר ואיתמר Elazar v'Isamar were כהנים הדיוטים kohanim hedyotim
who cannot do the עבודה avodah אונן. onein. אהרן Aharon is a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who can do the עבודה avodah אונן. onein.
You guys with me? Alright. So his response is הן היום הקריבו
את חטאתם ואת עלתם
hen hayom hikrivu es chatasam
v'es olasam okay blah blah blah. So the way the way we're
going to read it is the
following: הן היום... hen hayom... Meaning and Moshe said to Aaron, Moshe
was trying to sort of like help out Aaron. He said, maybe
the reason you burnt it was because
נדב ואביהו Nadav v'Avihu אלעזר ואיתמר Elazar v'Itamar were מקריב makriv it
and they were אוננים onanim after נדב ואביהו Nadav v'Avihu died and
maybe because they as כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot brought it, brought it
while they were אונן, onen, they invalidated it. A כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, that's what we're trying to sort of say here. A כהן
הדיוט kohen hedyot who brings it as an אונן onen invalidates. Okay,
and maybe that's why you had to burn it. And Aaron says
no, הן היום, Hen hayom, do you think they're the ones who
brought it today? No, I was the one who brought it and
I'm a כהן גדול kohen gadol and a כהן גדול kohen gadol
is allowed to bring it as an אונן. onen. So that's not
why it was burnt. So why was it burnt? Okay, so we'll
worry about that in a minute. But anyway, ואת דמי חטאתיהם כאלה.
V'et
d'mei chatateihem ka'eleh.
Okay, fine. With that, so what? You're an אונן, onen, אונן onen
was מקריב אונן, makriv onen? the כהן גדול kohen gadol is מקריב
makriv אונן. onen, Anyway, so if you read it this way, the
point is since it's read like no, they didn't do it, that's
not why, so if they had done it, it would have invalidated.
So you learn out that a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot who brings
as an אונן onen. invalidates.
Okay, so הן היום אני הקרבתי, Hen hayom ani hikravti, מכלל m'khlal
so that you can infer דאינהו אקריב de-inhu akriv if they had
been the ones who brought it, שפיר אישתרוף, shapir ishtarof, it would
have been good that it was burnt. Okay, for five. So those
are two ways of learning it out. One the both about the
fact that if a כהן גדול kohen gadol does it he's fine
and the inference being that if not a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot
does it it invalidates.
So the גמרא Gemara says רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, מאי טעמא לא
אמר ומן המקדש לא יצא? mai ta'ama lo amar u'min hamikdash lo
yetzei? Why do you have to go to the story about אהרן
Aharon and נדב ואביהו, Nadav v'Avihu, נדב ואביהו? Nadav v'Avihu? Why not
go to the story of the פסוק pasuk מן המקדש לא יצא?
min hamikdash lo yetzei? The כהן גדול kohen gadol doesn't go out
and doesn't invalidate, somebody else who doesn't go out does invalidate. So
the גמרא Gemara says ומן המקדש
לא יצא, u'min hamikdash lo yetzei, אמר לך מי כתיב האחר שלא
יצא חילל? amar lakh mi ktiv ha-acher shelo yatza chillel? Because it
doesn't tell you if somebody else goes out that they do invalidate.
Meaning this is the problem right? We normally think if P then
Q means if not P then not Q. But that's not true,
right? You could say like if the Mets win the World Series
I'll give you ten dollars. It doesn't mean if they don't win
I won't give you ten dollars. Maybe I will, maybe I won't.
Right? So anyway, so if a כהן גדול kohen gadol doesn't go
out he won't, he won't invalidate. If a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot
doesn't go out maybe he will, maybe he won't invalidate. You don't
know that it means that if a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot stays
he will invalidate. Maybe the פסוק pasuk is telling you the opposite.
כהן גדול kohen gadol who's so holy you might think that he
because his he would invalidate
because he's an אונן. onen No, even he doesn't invalidate. But a
כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot also doesn't invalidate. So you can't learn it
out from the fact that a כהן גדול kohen gadol doesn't invalidate
to assume that it means that a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot does
invalidate. That you can't get from the פסוק. pasuk. Okay.
Of course this you could say, I mean it's not clear here
either, but if we're going to read it, did they do it?
No, then you would have been right, I did it so you're
not right. So therefore then I mean obviously it's not in the
פסוק, pasuk, but the way we're choosing to read the פסוק pasuk
obviously could be said would imply that if they did it then
it would have invalidated it. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ואידך
מאי טעמא לא אמר מהן הקריבו? v'idakh mai ta'ama lo amar me-hen
hikrivu? So why not learn it out from הן הקריבו? hen hikrivu?
קסבר מפני טומאה נשרפה, kasavar mipnei tumah nisrefah, because he says that
the point is that you're misreading the פסוק. pasuk. The פסוק pasuk
is that it was burnt because it was טמא, tamei, it wasn't
burnt because of the אונן onen. issue and that's not how we
read the פסוק pasuk at all. Okay so I don't want to
get, so meaning let me just check רש"י Rashi quickly.
Oh, because the way we read it that way, the underscore is
not הן, hen, the underscore is הן היום. hen hayom. Meaning okay
and it's not really about being מקריב, makriv it's about when they
ate it. That basically the point is that an אונן onen according
to this reading an אונן onen is not allowed to eat the
קרבן korban the day of אנינות, aninut, but by the nighttime you're
allowed to eat. And according to this the reason it was burnt
was because since they didn't eat it during the day because during
the day they were אוננים, onanim, so they were leaving the meat
untended to and something happened it became טמא. tamei. So the reason
it became טמא tamei was because they didn't eat it during the
day. So therefore what אהרן Aharon is saying is not the underscore
of הן, hen, it's הן היום hen hayom הקריבו את חטאתם ואת
עלתם. hikrivu et chatatam v'et olatam. This was brought today while they
were אוננים onanim and therefore it couldn't be eaten today and that's
why it became טמא tamei and that's why we had to burn
it at night. Okay. So anyway, yeah so but don't worry we're
going to get to a whole section of the גמרא Gemara that's
going to unpack that whole debate between משה Moshe and אהרן. Aharon.
We're not going to unpack it now.
No no that's fine, but in terms to so no one's saying
that an אונן onen can bring it but then not necessarily eat
it? If you should bring it you eat it, can't just say
you do one but not the other?
That's correct, the כהן גדול kohen gadol brings it as an אונן
onen but does not eat it as an אונן. onen That's הלכה.
halakha. כהן גדול מקריב אונן ואינו אוכל. kohen gadol makriv onen v'eino
okhel.
Right, so then why can't that just be the answer? In other
words why wasn't it eaten? Because I'm an אונן. onen. I can
bring it.
It is the answer, that is the answer. That's the way this
reads. The reason it wasn't eat, but why was it burnt? Not
why wasn't it eaten? Why was it burnt?
Well if you don't eat it, then it becomes נותר notar and
you have to burn it.
That's only if you don't eat it at night. So that's the
explanation of אנינות aninus because if you hold אנינות לילה, aninus layla,
since we couldn't eat it today and not tonight, and by then
it would be נותר, notar, that's why we burnt it. So
those are the, that's the other version. Anyway, so we have two
ways of reading it. Either the inference from the כהן גדול kohen
gadol by the פסוק pasuk מן המקדש לא יצא min hamikdash lo
yetzei or by a way of reading the exchange of משה ואהרן.
Moshe v'Aharon. Either way, the point is the same. A כהן גדול
kohen gadol can bring it as an אונן, onen. a כהן הדיוט
kohen hedyot who brings it as an אונן onen, invalidates it. Okay.
Okay, דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא d'vei Rabbi Ishmael tana אתי קל וחומר
מבעל מום. ati kal vachomer mibal mum.
Okay, one is to learn a direct פסוק pasuk about that category,
about זר, zar, about אונן. onen The other is part of a
general rule that, you know, learn it out from בעל מום, ba'al
mum, make a general rule. ומה בעל מום שאוכל, uma ba'al mum
she'ochel, a בעל מום ba'al mum can even eat the קרבן korban
אם עבר חילל im avar chilel if he does the עבודה avoda
he, you know, he invalidates it. אונן שאינו אוכל, onen she'eino ochel,
an אונן onen. that doesn't eat, right, how much more so should
he invalidate? So that's your standard קל וחומר. kal vachomer. We're going
to learn it from בעל מום. ba'al mum. As you can guess,
we're pretty soon going to get to a צד השוה. tzad hashaveh.
Okay, fine. מה לבעל מום שכן עשה בו קרבנין כמקריבין, mah l'ba'al
mum sheken asah bo korbanin kemakrivin, same thing גמרא Gemara said yesterday.
No, בעל מום ba'al mum maybe has a greater power to invalidate
because the idea of מום mum applies not only to the כהן
kohen who brings it, but to the animal itself. So that's a
bigger problem. זר יוכיח. zar yochiach. Okay, no,
now
that we just got through proving it from a non-כהן, kohen, we'll
take an example about a זר. zar. The idea of a זר
zar doesn't apply to the קרבן, korban, obviously. You don't have to
have a קרבן korban being a כהן. kohen. Okay, anyway, so therefore
the combination of זר zar and בעל מום ba'al mum shows you
a general principle. מה לזר שכן אין לו תקנה. mah l'zar sheken
ein lo takana. Oh wait a minute, a זר zar you never
stop being a זר. zar. A בעל מום ba'al mum it could
be a מום עובר, mum over, it could be a temporary מום.
mum. בעל מום יוכיח. ba'al mum yochiach.
בעל מום ba'al mum and אונן onen I should say both have
תקנה, takana, right, a person will stop being an אונן onen by
the next day, and the בעל מום ba'al mum could be a
temporary מום. mum. So maybe therefore, you know, maybe a זר zar
is invalid, maybe that doesn't apply to an אונן, onen אונן's onen,
more temporary. So we say no, בעל מום יוכיח. ba'al mum yochiach.
A בעל מום ba'al mum will prove to you that even if
it's not permanent, it's a problem. וחזר הדין. v'chazar hadin. לא ראי
זה כראי זה ולא ראי זה כראי זה. lo rei zeh kirei
zeh v'lo rei zeh kirei zeh. Each one has its own distinctiveness.
The idea of a זר zar has an idea of permanent, maybe
that's more powerful. The idea of a מום mum has an idea
that it applies actually to the animals themselves, maybe that's more powerful.
But neither one has the other one's unique characteristics. הצד השוה שבהן,
hatsad hashaveh shebahen, the common denominator, שמוזהרים she'muzharim
that these are people that are not allowed to bring their קרבן
korban in this state, ואם עבדו חיללו v'im avdu chillilu
and if they do they desecrate it, they invalidate it. אף אני
אביא אונן aph ani avi onen I'll include an אונן onen's שמוזהר,
she'muzhar, he's not allowed, ואם עבר חילל v'im avar chilel and therefore
he desecrates it. So and therefore you cannot, so because of the
common denominator of a מום mum and a זר, zar, you're able
to pretty much now apply it to everything else. Okay, now, but
you have to then prove that these other statuses you're prohibited. Okay,
the צד השוה tzad hashaveh requires that you are prohibited against bringing
it in this state.
So the גמרא Gemara says היכן מוזהר? heichan muzhar? Now
where do you know an אונן onen is not allowed to bring
a קרבן? korban? So אילימא ממן המקדש לא יצא eileima mi'min hamikdash
lo yetzei that, you know, a כהן גדול kohen gadol doesn't go
out, that implies that somebody who's a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot does
have to go out and will invalidate. So of course if that's
where we're learning it from, we don't need the צד השוה. tzad
hashaveh. חילול בגופיה כתיב ביה. chilel begufei ketiv bei. So look, that
was our first לימוד. limud. Our first לימוד limud tried to learn
it from מן המקדש לא יצא, min hamikdash lo yetzei, then we
wouldn't need a צד השוה. tzad hashaveh. Then it's all packaged there.
It's implicit that a normal כהן kohen has to go out and
if a normal כהן kohen stays, he invalidates. The reason we're doing
a צד השוה tzad hashaveh is we're saying we don't want to
learn from that פסוק. pasuk. That פסוק pasuk doesn't, we're going to
say, doesn't speak about what the real הלכה halacha is by a
כהן הדיוט. kohen hedyot. So we're learning from a צד השוה. tzad
hashaveh. So how do you know that a normal כהן kohen who's
an אונן onen is prohibited?
אלא מהן הקריבו ela me'hen hikrivu וקסבר מפני אנינות נשרפה, v'kasavar mipnei
aninus nisrepha, so which seems to be also like why not just
learn it out from that itself as well. But again, from the
הן הקריבו, hen hikrivu, because again if you go back to the
saying of הן הקריבו, hen hikrivu, so the way רש''י Rashi explains
it is to read it this way it's like what, do you
think they did it? But it's not saying had they done it
they would have invalidated. That's not implicit in the פסוק. pasuk. What's
implicit in the פסוק pasuk is אהרן Aharon saying we didn't do
anything wrong because they weren't the ones who brought it, I was
the one who brought it. So therefore you can read the פסוק
pasuk this way and say that the issue is about being an
אונן onen and that's the emphasis, and אהרן Aharon is saying hey,
we didn't violate, they didn't bring it, I brought it. But still
not say the פסוק pasuk makes it clear that had they done
it
they would have invalidated. That we learn out. from the גזירה שוה.
Gezeirah Shavah. So this implies that you're not allowed to, and the
גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah tells you if you did it, you invalidated.
Because okay, איכא למפרך, Ika Lemifrach, ניחא nicha fine. So let's say
we got that. An אונן onen is not allowed and we make
a גזירה שוה. Gezeirah Shavah. But the גזירה שוה Gezeirah Shavah maybe
won't apply to אונן. Onen There's a unique aspect of בעל מום
Baal Mum and a זר Zar that doesn't apply to an אונן.
Onen. What is that? מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן לא הותרו מכללו.
Mah Lehatzad Hashaveh Shebahen Sheken Lo Hutru Miklalo. Okay, a זר Zar
and a non-כהן Kohen have exceptions. Oh, excuse me, excuse me, a
זר, Zar, excuse me I said that wrong. No, a זר Zar
is a non-כהן. Kohen. A זר Zar and a בעל מום Baal
Mum don't have exceptions. A זר Zar is never כשר Kasher in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and a מום Mum is never כשר
Kasher in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay? Whereas an אונן Onen.
is כשר Kasher in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Which אונן Onen
is כשר Kasher in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. Okay, so you can't say, "Oh, since a זר Zar and
a בעל מום Baal Mum invalidate, the same as an אונן." Onen
Since there's cases where an אונן Onen. is okay, an אונן כהן
גדול, Onen Kohen Gadol, maybe even as an אונן הדיוט, Onen Hedyot,
it won't invalidate. Okay, because an אונן Onen is not completely off
limits in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so
איכא למפרך. Ika Lemifrach. מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן לא הותרו מכללו.
Mah Lehatzad Hashaveh Shebahen Sheken Lo Hutru Miklalo. טמא יוכיח. Tamei Yochiach.
Ah, so throw טמא Tamei into the mix. Because טמא Tamei we
know invalidates and טמא Tamei does have exceptions in the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. When can a כהן Kohen who's טמא Tamei do the
עבודה Avodah in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Right, if it's טומאה
הותרה בציבור, Tumah Hutra Betzibbur, if everybody is טמא Tamei or... okay,
and it's a קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibbur. All right? So therefore you
have cases which are sometimes allowed and still invalidate a טמא, Tamei,
and therefore the same should be true by an
אונן. Onen מה לטמא שכן מטמא? Mah Letamei Sheken Metamei? Oh, but
wait, טמא Tamei has the power to invalidate because a טמא Tamei
makes other things טמא. Tamei. הנך יוכיחו וחזר הדין. Hanch Yochichu Vechazar
Hadin. Fine, not just by טמא, Tamei, you throw it into the
mix. Just by טמא Tamei you'd have a way to bracket it,
but טמא Tamei and בעל מום Baal Mum and a זר Zar
and all those things, so we get a general צד השוה. Tzad
Hashaveh. You can't bracket it into any unique box. The general צד
השוה Tzad Hashaveh is you're not allowed and you invalidate and don't
try to say that only applies to things that don't have exceptions,
because טמא Tamei has an exception. Even things that do have exceptions
invalidate and therefore the same is true by an אונן. Onen. Okay.
Okay, where were we? הצד השוה שבהן שכן הם אסורין... Hatzad Hashaveh
Shebahen Sheken Hem Asurin... ולפרוך. Velifrach. מה להצד השוה שבהן שכן לא
הותרו מכללן אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד. Mah Lehatzad Hashaveh Shebahen Sheken
Lo Hutru Miklalan Etzel Kohen Gadol Bekorban Yachid. So that's very narrow.
Ah, one minute, we could say all those things including טמא, Tamei,
they never are מותר Mutar by a קרבן יחיד Korban Yachid by
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So the common denominator is, we sort
of like create the common denominator to be they're not an אונן.
Onen. Okay? The common denominator is that there's never an exception made
for them by a private קרבן, Korban, because even טמא, Tamei, the
exception is only by קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibbur. Whereas אונן, Onen. an
exception is made by a private קרבן Korban by a case of
a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. So maybe therefore you can't apply it
to אונן, Onen, because אונן Onen, actually has an exception even in
a case of a private קרבן. Korban. So the גמרא Gemara says
בשם טומאה מיהא אישתרי. Beshem Tumah Miha Ishtari. No, I'm not impressed
by that, says the גמרא. Gemara. If an exception is made then
an exception is made, and since an exception is made by טומאה
Tumah and it still invalidates, then even though exceptions are made by
אונן Onen it will also still invalidate. Yes.
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is not considered a private קרבן? Korban?
That is correct, it's considered enough of the גמרא Gemara discusses that,
technically it's a private one but because everybody's bringing it at the
same time it's considered like a קרבן ציבור. Korban Tzibbur. And actually
the real secret is that you don't even really need it to
be a קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur to override, you really need it
to be a קרבן Korban with a fixed time, שקבוע לו זמן.
Shekavuah Lo Zeman. קרבן ציבור Korban Tzibbur is a bit of a
misnomer. Anyway, רב משרשיא אמר אתיא בקל וחומר מיושב. Rav Mesharshiya Amar
Atya Bekal Vachomer Miyoshev.
Let's make it based on יושב. Yoshev. Okay, and eventually we're going
to circle back and make it a צד השוה. Tzad Hashaveh. Okay,
there's a very similar pattern to all these גמרות. Gemorot. מה יושב
שאוכל אם עבד חילל אונן שאינו אוכל אינו דין שאם עבד
חילל. Mah Yoshev She'ochel Im Avad Chillel Onen She'eino Ochel Eino Din
She'im Avad Chillel. יושב, Yoshev, somebody sitting
who can eat the קרבן Korban but he invalidates. So an אונן
Onen who can't eat certainly invalidates. מה ליושב שכן פסול לעדות? Mah
Leyoshev Sheken Pasul Le'eidus? So, ah, but one minute, a יושב Yoshev
is more powerful, it's invalid even to testify. For whatever reason that's
relevant. מיושב תלמיד חכם. Miyoshev Talmid Chacham. Oh, יושב תלמיד חכם, Yoshev
Talmid Chacham, he can testify, and therefore
so you can't try to limit it that way. No. לשם יושב
שכן פסול לעדות. Leshem Yoshev Sheken Pasul Le'eidus. Okay, but at least
there's some יושב Yoshev that is invalid for עדות Eidus and therefore
it's more powerful and you can't learn from it. לשם יושב לא
פרך. Leshem Yoshev Lo Parach. All right, that doesn't impress him. The
fact is that there are some יושבs Yoshev that are good, so
don't try to limit it that way. ואם תימצי לומר פרך. Ve'im
Timtzi Lomar Parach. And if you do want to learn it, say
that you can't learn it from יושב Yoshev alone because יושב Yoshev
is more powerful because of this עדות Eidus thing, so אתיא מיושב
ומחד מהנך. Atya Miyoshev Umichad Mehanach.
Make it as a צד השוה Tzad Hashaveh from יושב Yoshev and
one of the other ones. Okay, and again, the general rule is
somebody that is prohibited therefore is, you know, is not allowed and
therefore is prohibited, invalidates, and then don't try to limit it by
saying what do we try to limit it? Remember we tried to
limit it by saying what do you call it? No no, tried
to limit it by saying הותרה
מכללו hutra miklolo that there are exceptions. Well, there's no
הותרה מכללו hutra miklolo by
יושב, yoshev, by sitting. Oh no, no, that's excuse me, that's exactly
Tosfos's question, that if you're just learning it out from יושב, yoshev,
the Gemara could have said the same if you look at this
little Tosfos, עשה בקל וחומר מיושב, aso be-kal vachomer mi-yoshev, Tosfos says,
תימא מה ליושב שכן לא הותרה מכללו. teima ma le-yoshev she-kein lo
hutra miklolo. The Gemara,
why was the Gemara happy when it said יושב? yoshev? You could
have said one minute,
sitting is never allowed, so don't say learn it as a צד
שוה tzad shaveh from I don't know, like sitting in a בעל
מום, baal mum, because no exceptions are ever made, whereas by an
אונן, Onen whereas by, you know, whereas by an אונן, onein, exceptions
are made. So in the end, right, that's what bothered the Gemara
before. So in the end, it's not clear why the Gemara's happier
by introducing יושב. yoshev. At the end of the day, you throw
in enough of the people that are invalid, and therefore you can't
put anyone in a box. Okay? And the most we would try
to the box we would try to sort of say is, you
can't apply it to an אונן onein, because exceptions are made by
an אונן, onein and therefore maybe it doesn't invalidate, and for that
you have to throw in the case of טומאה. tumah. If you
throw in the case of טמא, tamei, so טמא tamei exceptions are
made, and nevertheless it invalidates, that allowed us now to say that
an אונן onein, even though exceptions are made invalidates. Okay, so either
you have a specific פסוק, pasuk, like הן היום hein hayom or
by the כהן גדול kohein gadol where it says
מן המקדש לא יצא, mina mikdash lo yetzei, or you don't have
a specific פסוק, pasuk, you have a general principle. Anybody who is
not allowed invalidates. And then when you try to limit that to
say somehow wait, there's something here that's unique, if you throw in
enough cases, you won't be able to exclude the case we're dealing
with. Okay? So don't exclude אונן onein because there are exceptions, throw
in טמא tamei and a טמא tamei person where there's also exceptions,
and that also invalidates, so אונן onein as well will invalidate. Okay,
so now the Gemara continues. אמר רבא. Amar Rava.
Now this gets a little sort of complicated, well I don't know.
אמר רבא, לא שנו אלא בקרבן יחיד אבל בקרבן ציבור מרצה. Amar
Rava, lo shanu ela be-korban yachid aval be-korban tzibur meratzeh. Now Rava's
going to try to say that idea that an אונן onein invalidates
is only by a קרבן יחיד, korban yachid, by a private korban.
But by a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur actually an אונן onein will
be good. Why is that?
Even a non-כהן גדול. kohein gadol.
Even a non-כהן גדול, kohein gadol, right. So he's going to do
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. קל וחומר מטומאה, מה טומאה שלא הותרה
מכללו אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד הותרה אצל הדיוט בקרבן ציבור. kal
vachomer mi-tumah, ma tumah she-lo hutra miklolo etzel kohein gadol be-korban yachid
hutra etzel hedyot be-korban tzibur.
So let's make a chart here, okay? So we've got here כהן
הדיוט, kohein hedyot, okay, and a case of טומאה. tumah. Okay, and
here we've got כהן גדול kohein gadol and a case of אונן.
onein Okay, so now if you have a case of, so here
ציבור tzibur is check, יחיד, קרבן יחיד yachid, korban yachid is no
good. Okay, here
ציבור tzibur is
good
and יחיד, yachid, well we're going to assume is, wait what does
Rava say one more time? לא שנו אלא בקרבן יחיד אבל בקרבן
ציבור מרצה. lo shanu ela be-korban yachid aval be-korban tzibur meratzeh. קרבן
ציבור, korban tzibur, oh we're going to
anyway
fine,
we're going to assume that that's good in fact, okay? So כהן
גדול kohein gadol whether ציבור tzibur or יחיד yachid is good, and
כהן הדיוט kohein hedyot it's only a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur that's
good, right? Everybody get that by טומאה? tumah? Okay, by טומאה. tumah.
Now we're trying to prove what's going to be the story by
a כהן הדיוט kohein hedyot by אונן. onein. Okay, that's what we're
going to try to figure out. And he's going to try to
say that it's good by a קרבן ציבור korban tzibur by אונן
onein. by a כהן הדיוט. kohein hedyot. Let's see the קל וחומר.
kal vachomer. Okay? So,
קל וחומר מטומאה, מה
טומאה
שלא הותרה מכללו אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד...
kal vachomer mi-tumah, ma tumah she-lo
hutra miklolo etzel kohein gadol be-korban yachid... yeah, well
okay, fine, ah sorry. I don't know.
It may be easier if you just make like a grid, two
boxes by two boxes, you know what I mean?
How do you think I should make it? I'm getting confused. All
right,
let's just let's try to do it based
on, you know, טומאה tumah then אנינות, aninus, כהן גדול, כהן, kohein
gadol, kohein, you know, axis.
Fine, let's try that.
No, but there's three. There's כהן גדול, kohein gadol, כהן הדיוט, kohein
hedyot, טומאה, tumah, אנינות, aninus, and ציבור tzibur and יחיד. yachid. Yeah,
then you can try
two by two by each.
All right, let's try it that way. טומאה, tumah, I should have
figured this out ahead of time. I thought I had it in
my head but I guess I didn't. Okay.
כהן גדול kohein gadol and כהן הדיוט. kohein hedyot. Let's try it
that way. Okay, let's see what let's see if that gets it
to us. Okay.
Okay. אבל בקרבן ציבור מרצה, aval be-korban tzibur meratzeh, קל וחומר
מטומאה, מה טומאה שלא הותרה מכללו אצל כהן הדיוט בקרבן יחיד... kal
vachomer mi-tumah, ma tumah she-lo hutra miklolo etzel kohein hedyot be-korban yachid...
כהן גדול, טומאה. kohein gadol, tumah. So ציבור tzibur obviously is check,
that doesn't need to be a כהן גדול. kohein gadol. Right here
too, ציבור, tzibur, טומאה. tumah. טומאה tum'ah is a check. But by
a יחיד, yachid, okay, there's no היתר heter of טומאה tum'ah by
a יחיד yachid even by a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Okay, so
הותרה אצל הדיוט בקרבן ציבור, hutra etzel hedyot bekorban tzibur, so here,
okay, ציבור tzibur by a כהן kohen it makes, so something that
by כהן גדול kohen gadol ביחיד beyachid is no good, by כהן
הדיוט kohen hedyot בציבור betzibur is good. Okay.
אנינות שהותרה מכללה אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד, aninus shehutra mikhlala etzel
kohen gadol bekorban yachid, so אונן onein whether it's ציבור tzibur or
יחיד, yachid, right, is good for a כהן גדול kohen gadol is
good. So שהותרה... shehutra... אינו
דין שהותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בקרבן ציבור. eino din shehutra etzel kohen
hedyot bekorban tzibur. How much more so, okay, should this be? Ah,
okay. So here,
when it comes to טומאה, tum'ah, it's not a total blanket okay
by a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, and ציבור tzibur is okay, right,
even though it's not a total blanket okay. So when it comes
to אנינות aninus where it's a blanket okay by כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, right, even the case of יחיד yachid is okay, how much
more so should ציבור tzibur be okay by a כהן הדיוט. kohen
hedyot. That's the argument. You with... okay, you with me?
I'm with you, I'm not really...
and you're not buying it. You're not buying it. Okay, fine. Well
the גמרא Gemara doesn't buy it either. Okay. Because the גמרא Gemara
says as long as you're doing that, you can come to a
lot of other possible
conclusions, alright? So let's take a look. Okay.
מתקיף לה רבא בר אהילאי. maskif lah Rava bar Ahilai. רבא בר
אהילאי Rava bar Ahilai challenges: לא תותר lo tutar asay if you're
willing to make that types of קל וחומר, kal vachomer, what why
do you come out to change that parameters? There's a lot of
other parameters you could theoretically, you know, you could come to a
lot of other possible conclusions. לא תותר אנינות אצל כהן גדול בקרבן
יחיד מקל וחומר. lo tutar aninus etzel kohen gadol bekorban yachid mikal
vachomer. I'm going to say that אונן onen by a יחיד yachid
maybe this should be the one that we don't know. Okay, and
maybe this is the one we should say X. Now that's obviously
the פשט pshat we assume not that way. The פשט pshat we
assume is that you have a blanket היתר heter by an אונן.
onen Of course, the פשט pshat is also that we assume that
אנינות aninus doesn't apply at all to a כהן גדול. kohen gadol.
So as long as you're willing to say things that are not
explicit are are up for grabs, I'll say okay, maybe I'll come
to a conclusion that a כהן גדול kohen gadol יחיד yachid אונן
onen. is no good. The תורה Torah only allowed a קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibur. How would I come to that conclusion? Well, just follow
this.
Okay. He says like this.
מקל וחומר, mikal vachomer, ומה טומאה שהותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בציבור לא
הותרה אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד, uma tum'ah shehutra etzel kohen hedyot
betzibur lo hutra etzel kohen gadol bekorban yachid, so טומאה tum'ah which
is good here בציבור, betzibur, okay, is not good by כהן גדול
kohen gadol ביחיד. beyachid. So something that's so if it's good here
it's still not good there. So אנינות
שלא הותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בקרבן ציבור, aninus shelo hutra etzel kohen
hedyot bekorban tzibur, here, אנינות aninus which is not meaning here meaning
rather you're trying you were trying to say let's make this good.
I'm going to start with the opposite assumption. I'm going to switch
everybody normally assumes, okay, that a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot nothing is
okay by אנינות. aninus. Alright? So if I'm going to start with
the assumption that כהן גדול kohen gadol is not okay by אנינות
aninus I'll say like this. Here where ציבור tzibur is good, יחיד
yachid is not good, right, by טומאה tum'ah ציבור tzibur is good
by הדיוט hedyot it's not good טומאה tum'ah by a כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. So here where ציבור tzibur is not good, if I
start with that assumption, then I'll make a קל וחומר kal vachomer
that יחיד yachid will not be good by an אונן. onen Okay.
So you assumed if this was a check this was an X.
If this was a check excuse me, what did you assume? You
assumed I don't now I'm getting confused. You assumed if this was
a check this was a check, I'm going to assume if this
is an X that's an X. Okay.
So you might ask how do we learn then a כהן גדול
kohen gadol קרבן יחיד korban yachid can be
like מקריב makriv, אונן?
onen. Because a פסוק pasuk just says מן המקדש לא יצא. min
hamikdash lo yetzei. Okay, why should we limit the פסוק pasuk to
a קרבן ציבור? korban tzibur? Okay, anyway, but that's what we're trying
to debate, maybe we should limit it. Okay, so,
okay. ומה טומאה שהותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בציבור לא הותרה אצל כהן
גדול בקרבן יחיד, uma tum'ah shehutra etzel kohen hedyot betzibur lo hutra
etzel kohen gadol bekorban yachid, אנינות שהותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בציבור אינו
דין שלא תותר אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד. aninus shehutra etzel kohen
hedyot betzibur eino din shelo tutar etzel kohen gadol bekorban yachid. And
now, now, or I'll say something else. ותותר טומאה אצל כהן גדול
בקרבן יחיד מקל וחומר. vetutar tum'ah etzel kohen gadol bekorban yachid mikal
vachomer. So
let me actually say that maybe I will sort of say rather
than assuming that that's an X, maybe I'm going to sort of
figure out maybe I'll find a way to say that a כהן
גדול kohen gadol טומאה tum'ah יחיד yachid should be okay. How am
I going to find a way to say that? Well, let's do
this. Okay. ותותר vetutar where where where... מקל וחומר, mikal vachomer, ומה
אנינות שלא הותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בקרבן ציבור, uma aninus shelo hutra
etzel kohen hedyot bekorban tzibur, טומאה שלא הותרה אצל כהן הדיוט... tum'ah
shelo hutra etzel kohen hedyot... wait...
wait a minute... ומה אנינות שהותרה אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד, uma
aninus shehutra etzel kohen gadol bekorban yachid, right? So now, we're going
to start by assuming that that's no good, which is of course
the פשט, pshat, that there's no היתר heter of אנינות aninus for
a כהן הדיוט kohen hedyot even by ציבור? tzibur? No. Okay, so
that's not good. הותרה אצל כהן גדול בקרבן יחיד, hutra etzel kohen
gadol bekorban yachid, but we're going to assume, which is also the
פשט, pshat, that it's going to be okay by כהן גדול. kohen
gadol. Okay, so when ציבור tzibur is no good by a כהן
הדיוט kohen hedyot by אנינות, aninus,
it's good by a case here by a... כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*,
right, by יחיד *yachid*. So here where ציבור *tzibur* is good by
טומאה *tumah*, it should certainly be good by a כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol* יחיד *yachid*. Right? If here's an X and here's a plus,
then if here's a plus, there should certainly be a plus. And
then it'll come to the conclusion that a כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*
for by טומאה *tumah* by יחיד *yachid* is מותר *mutar*, which is
also, also not true. Okay, depending on which parameter you keep as
an, as a given, you can come to a different conclusion for
another one. No, we're not asking any questions right now. Okay. טומאה
שהותרה אצל כהן הדיוט בקורבן ציבור אינו דין שתותרה אצל כהן גדול
בקורבן יחיד *Tumah she'hutra etzel Kohen Hedyot bekorban tzibur eini din she'tutre
etzel Kohen Gadol bekorban yachid*? Okay, third possibility. ולא תותר טומאה אצל
כהן הדיוט בקורבן ציבור מקל וחומר *V'lo tutar tumah etzel Kohen Hedyot
bekorban tzibur mikal v'chomer*. טומאה אצל כהן הדיוט בקורבן ציבור *Tumah etzel
Kohen Hedyot bekorban tzibur*. Ah, let me actually assume that maybe the
whole היתר *heter* of טומאה בציבור *tumah be'tzibur*, maybe that doesn't apply
to, you know, maybe that's only limited to a כהן גדול *Kohen
Gadol*. That's going to be interesting. The whole time we talk about
טומאה הותרה בציבור *tumah hutra be'tzibur* we're going to limit it to
a כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. Okay, we're going to say a כהן
הדיוט בציבור *Kohen Hedyot be'tzibur* is not good. How are you going
to say that?
So here's the קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. Where,
where am I? ולא תותר טומאה אצל כהן הדיוט בקורבן ציבור מקל
וחומר *V'lo tutar tumah etzel Kohen Hedyot bekorban tzibur mikal v'chomer*. ומה
אנינות שהותרה אצל כהן גדול בקורבן יחיד *U'ma aninus she'hutre etzel Kohen
Gadol bekorban yachid*, אנינות שהותרה אצל כהן גדול *aninus she'hutzru etzel Kohen
Gadol*, okay, אנינות *aninus* you have a blanket okay by a כהן
גדול *Kohen Gadol*, even by יחיד *yachid*, לא הותרה אצל כהן הדיוט
בקורבן ציבור *lo hutzre etzel Kohen Hedyot bekorban tzibur*, so it goes
this way. Here it's a plus because this may, this is a
good place to start, right? אונן *Onen* is good by a כהן
גדול *Kohen Gadol*, has no היתר *heter* by a כהן הדיוט *Kohen
Hedyot*. So if this is a plus and if even when this
is a plus, this is going to be an X, so when
this is an X, טומאה *tumah* by כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol* קל
וחומר *kal v'chomer* so is that going to be an X, טומאה
בציבור בכהן הדיוט *tumah be'tzibur be'Kohen Hedyot*. Okay, so אצל כהן הדיוט
בקורבן ציבור *etzel Kohen Hedyot bekorban tzibur*, טומאה שלא הותרה אצל כהן
גדול בקורבן יחיד אינו דין שלא תותרה בכהן הדיוט בקורבן ציבור *tumah
she'lo hutzre etzel Kohen Gadol bekorban yachid eini din she'lo tutar be'Kohen
Hedyot bekorban tzibur*? Okay, so בקיצור *bekitzur*, you can come to a
lot of different conclusions based on which parameter you're going to start
assume to begin with and which one you're going to say is
open for discussion. אלא איכא למיפרך הכי ואיכא למיפרך הכי *Ella ika
l'mifrach hachi v'ika l'mifrach hachi*. You can make a lot of different
קל וחומרים *kal v'chomers* depending on where you start, you don't know
which one to start with, and therefore כוחא דהכא תיקום בדוכתיה *kocha
d'hacha tichu be'duchtei*. Don't make any קל וחומרים *kal v'chomers*. Just keep
things the פשט *pshat*, and the פשט *pshat* is that טומאה *tumah*
is about ציבור *tzibur*, okay, and טומאה *tumah*'s only limited to the
idea of ציבור *tzibur*, that's what טומאה *tumah*'s about, and אונן *onen*
is only limited to the idea of כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*. Okay,
it's a principle of כהן גדול *Kohen Gadol*, אונן *onen* is the
exception, טומאה ציבור *tumah tzibur* is the exception. Don't try to put
them into a grid and point out קל וחומרים *kal v'chomers* and
then make exceptions within the exceptions, okay, because then you'll have no
idea where to start and where to end. Mike had a question?
Yeah, my question before was we say that אונן *onen*, the כהן
גדול *Kohen Gadol*,
it's okay. Does it mean that he must or that he can?
Stay in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*?
No, meaning that if he wants to do the עבודה *avodah* that
he can, or like you know the חביתין *chavitzin* that he has
to bring every day. Does he have to do that when he's
אונן *onen* or could he say, "Alright, if I do it, it's
okay, but I can like skip today because like you know I
really don't want
to have to do it." No, I mean ומן המקדש לא יצא
*u'min hamikdash lo yeitzei*, if he's not already in the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash*. No, but he can't skip the קורבנות *korbanot* that he
has to bring, no, I mean the ones that he's חייב *chayav*
to bring, but the חביתין *chavitzin* are really they have to be
brought on his behalf. I don't think he has to be the
one to do the עבודה *avodah* of the חביתין *chavitzin*.
So if he's, so he
can skip it and you can skip? But he's not allowed to
be יוצא *yotzei*, that's an explicit פסוק *pasuk*, ומן המקדש לא יצא
*u'min hamikdash lo yeitzei*, if he becomes טמא *tamei*, but not like
go home, right?
He can't go after the מיטה
*mita*, but I'm saying like... I, I have to check the exact
parameters of that. I don't, I don't remember off hand. I'm, I'm
just, I understand your question, I'm telling you I don't know the
answer off the top of my head. Yes, Charlie.
I'm not used to seeing Rava get this badly refuted.
What can I tell you? It's a very good response. Okay, we
will end here.